# **Ana Samperiz Vizcaino**

(+44) 7721 604902 <a href="mailto:samperizvizcainoa@cardiff.ac.uk">samperizvizcainoa@cardiff.ac.uk</a>
School of Earth and Environmental Sciences, Cardiff University.

Main Building, Park Place, Cardiff, CF10 3AT

<a href="https://anasamperiz.github.io">https://anasamperiz.github.io</a>

# **Education**

# Cardiff University, Cardiff (United Kingdom)

PhD in Earth Sciences

October 2018 – Present

Thesis title: From watersheds to reef: reconstructing the history of land use change and coral reef health in Fiji.

Experience highlights:

- Processing of computerised tomography (CT) images for coral growth quantification.
- LA-ICP-MS trace metals analyses of coral skeletal material to explore environmental impacts.
- Work closely with international collaborators (WCS, USP Fiji, Government of Fiji).
- Outreach and science communication: Volunteering at "Pint of Science 2019". Implementation
  of a workshop on the topic "tropical reefs and corals as archives" aimed at both Primary and
  Secondary schools.

Funded by: NERC GW+4 DTP + CASE Partner Wildlife Conservation Society Fiji.

#### University of Bristol, Bristol (United Kingdom)

MSci by Research in Earth Sciences

September 2016 - August 2018 (Part time)

Thesis title: Stylasterid corals: A new paleoceanographic archive?

Experience highlights:

- Identification of stylasterid corals up to species level based on the skeletal morphology of the specimens.
- Sample selection and preparation for skeletal  $\delta^{13}$ C and  $\delta^{18}$ O analyses.
- Mineralogical analyses (XRD) and SEM imaging to determine biomineralisation patterns.
- Five-week marine research expedition onboard the RSS Discovery to the Labrador Sea.
- Outreach and science communication: execution of geology workshops aimed towards Primary Schools.

## University of Zaragoza, Huesca (Spain)

BSc Environmental Sciences, 1st class.

September 2009 - December 2014

Fourth year project title: *Design, implementation, and evaluation of an Environmental Education Program in a summer camp.* 

Experience highlights:

 Design of environmental education activities and obtention of data (quantitative and qualitative) to investigate their impact on participant's knowledge and behaviour towards the environment.

# Relevant employment

## **University of Bristol, Bristol (United Kingdom)**

Research analyst in marine geochemistry October 2016 – August 2018 (Part-time) Responsibilities:

- Physical and chemical cleaning of marine samples and preparation for AMS and MC-ICP-MS analyses.
- Curation of marine samples and maintenance of the coral database.
- Interaction with international collaborators and training visitors to the lab.

### Sustainability Office. University of Zaragoza, Zaragoza (Spain)

Environmental Education officer January 2013 – January 2015 Responsibilities:

> Design of environmental awareness campaigns directed to the university community, design and implementation of training courses about good environmental practices, events and conferences organization, web page and social media management.

#### Lab skills

- Data acquisition through computerised tomography (CT) and processing of CT images.
- Laser Ablation (LA) 193nm excimer laser.
- Analysis of trace elements in biogenic carbonates with LA ICPMS and data processing.
- Stable isotope ( $\delta^{13}$ C and  $\delta^{18}$ O) analysis in marine carbonates.
- Stylasterid and scleractinian corals morphological identification up to species level.
- Experience in chemistry clean laboratory.
- Environmental data acquisition through remote sensing (satellite data level 2 and level 3).

# **Technical skills**

- R: For tidying data, statistical analysis, data visualization and spatial analysis. Reproducible research and version control on R Markdown + GIT.
- ArcGIS and QGIS: Analysis of spatial data and data visualization.
- Corel, Inkscape + GIMP: For graphical enhancement of data visualization.
- Ocean Data View (ODV): For data visualization.

## **Publications**

- Li, T., Robinson, L., Chen, T., Wang, X., Burke, A., Rae, J., Pegrum-Haram, A., Knowles, T., Li, G., Chen, J., Ng, HC., Prokopenko, M., Rowland, G., Samperiz, A., Stewart, J., Southon, J., Spooner, P. 2020. Rapid shifts in circulation and biogeochemistry of the Southern Ocean during deglacial carbon cycle events. *Science Advances*, 6:42. doi:10.1126/sciadv.abb3807
- Samperiz, A., Robinson, L., Stewart, J., Strawson, I., Leng, M., Rosenheim, B., Ciscato, E., Hendry, K., Santodomingo, N. 2020. Stylasterid corals: a new paleotemperature archive. *Earth and Planetary Science Letters*, 545:116407. doi:10.1016/j.epsl.2020.116407

- Stewart, J., Robinson, L., Day, R., Strawson, I., Burke, A., Rae, J., Spooner, P., Samperiz, A., Etnoyer, P., Williams., B., Paytan, A., Leng, M., Häussermann, V., Wickes, L., Bratt, R., Pryer, H. 2020. Refining trace metal temperature proxies in cold-water scleractinian and stylasterid corals. *Earth and Planetary Science Letters*, 545:116412. doi:10.1016/j.epsl.2020.116412
- Hendry, K., Huvenne, V., Robinson, L., Annett, A., Badger, M., Jacobel, A. Ng, HC., Opher, J., Pickering, R., Taylor, M., Bates, S., Cooper, A., Cushman, G., Goodwin, C., Hoy, S., Rowland, G., Samperiz, A., Williams, J., Achterberg, E., Arrowsmith, C., Brearley, A., Henley, S., Krause, J., Leng, M., Li, T., McManus, J, Meredith, M., Perkins, R., Woodward, M. 2018. The biogeochemical impact of glacial meltwater from Southwest Greenland. *Progress in Oceanography*, 176:102126. doi:10.1016/j.pocean.2019.102126
- Samperiz, A. & Herrero, J. 2018. Evaluation of a summer camp environmental education program in Spain. Applied Environmental Education & Communication, 17(1), 79-90. doi:10.1080/1533015X.2017.1366881

# Teaching experience – Cardiff University

- Student supervision:
  - Mr Jacob Lloyd Newman: MSci research dissertation "Potential drivers of bioerosion in massive *Porites* on an inshore reef in Fiji".
- Teaching assistant during practical sessions in undergraduate modules:
  - Marine Environmental Systems (Year 2021-2022)
  - o Coral Reefs (Year 2020-2021)
  - o Coral Reefs (Year 2020-2021)
  - o Biogeochemistry (Years 2019-2020, 2020-2021)
  - o Earth surface processes (Year 2018-2019)

### **Invited talks**

- Sclerochronology group, University of Exeter April 2021
  - "Small but mighty: The potential of stylasterid corals as paleoceanographic archives" "Small but might: The potential of stylasterid corals as paleoceanographic archives"
- ECR symposium, International Fossil Coral and Reef Society (IFCRS) October 2021
  - "Small but might: The potential of stylasterid corals as paleoceanographic archives"

## **Awards and Grants**

- Hazel Prichard Impact Prize, School of Earth and Ocean Sciences, Cardiff University (2019). £500 to support the implementation of the outreach activity "REEFsistence".
- Alumni Foundation Award, University of Bristol (2017). £1,000 to support the outreach program
   "Rock Wow Days".
- Best 4<sup>th</sup> Year Project Award, Polytechnic School, University of Zaragoza (2015).

<sup>&</sup>quot;Stylasterid corals: A new paleotemperature archive."

# **Conference organization**

- Geochemistry Group Research in Progress (GGRiP) May 2022
- EARTH 3-minute talks, a flash-seminar series of flash seminars from the PGR community June to December 2021.